A Guide to Manuscript Poems by Longfellow, Lowell, Emerson, Holmes, Thoreau, Whittier Bryant, Aldrich and Other Famous American Poets
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Manuscript Poems by Longfellow, Lowell, Emerson, Holmes, Thoreau, Whittier Bryant, Aldrich and Other Famous American Poets 1845-1889
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6329-a
1 bound volume
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, December 1974
Scope and Content
A collection of American poems and songs bound in a volume, including manuscripts and portraits of authors.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  Bound folio of ca. 120 pages; items listed in order of appearance in the volume
  - Henry Wadsworth Longfellow: "All are architects of fate ...." quatrain, 1851 Aug 30; AMsS, 1 p.
  - James Russell Lowell: "For humanity sweeps onwards ..." 5-line stanza from "The crisis", 1886 Mar 4; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Francis Hodgson Burnett: "The status." [on verso of Lowell], n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Ralph Waldo Emerson: "As sings the pine in the wind ...." quatrain, AMsS, 1 p.
  - Oliver Wendell Holmes: "Old Ironsides," first stanza, 1889 May 24; AMsS, 1 p.
  - William Cullen Bryant: "Throw it aside in thy weary hour ...." quatrain, 1875 Mar 23; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Henry David Thoreau: "Fog" [published version is called "Mist"], n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - John Greenleaf Whittier: 20 lines from "The prisoner for debt", 1860 n.m. 6; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Thomas Bailey Aldrich: "An untimely thought", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - Julia Ward Howe: "Oh lordly, velvet-coated Hig-", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Lucy Larcom: "The beckoning west", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Richard Henry Stoddard: "Buried in songs that never yet were sung", [18]76 Feb 8; AMsS, 2 p.
  - John Boyle O'Reilly: "To-day", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Celia Thaxter: "To *****" ["Seaward"], n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Paul Hamilton Hayne: "The renegade", [1884]; AMsS, 1 p.
  - James T. Fields: "Our good-night kiss", 1845 May 6; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Edith M. Thomas: "The interpreter", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - William Dean Howells: "Thanksgiving", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Thomas William Parsons: "To a magnolia flower", [ca. 1860]; AMsS, 1 p.
  - George H. Boker: "Dirge for a soldier", 1889 Jan 21; AMsS, 4 p.
  - Edgar Fawcett: "The punishment", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wentworth Higginson :"Sixty and six" or "The fountain of youth", AMs, 3 p.
  - William Winter: "Orgis: the song of a ruined man", n.d.; AMsS, 5 p.
  - Edmund C. Stedman: "Guests at Yule", AMsS, 3 p.
- Portraits
  listed in order of appearance in the volume
  - Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, signed, [1807]; Portrait
  - James Russell Lowell, signed; also signed by Oliver Wendell Holmes, [1865]; Portrait
  - Ralph Waldo Emerson, n.d.; Portrait
  - Oliver Wendell Holmes, Portrait
  - William Cullen Bryant, n.d.; Portrait
  - John Greenleaf Whittier, n.d.; Portrait
  - Thomas Bailey Aldrich, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - Julia Ward Howe, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - Lucy Larcom, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - Celia Thaxter, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - Paul Hamilton Hayne, n.d.; Portrait
  - James T. Fields, Nathaniel Hawthorne, James Ripley Osgood, n.d.; Portrait
  - Edith M. Thomas, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - William Dean Howells, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - George H. Boker, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - Edgar Fawcett, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - Thomas Wentworth Higginson, signed, n.d.; Portrait
  - William Winter, n.d.; Portrait
  - Edmund C. Stedman, Portrait